Okay, בוקר טוב tov. *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *daf* is צדי ו"ו
*Tzadi Vav* and we pick up at the bottom of צדי ה'
עמוד ב' *Tzadi Hey Amud Bet*. We had a cryptic statement in
the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosei* that
basically said, he made a statement to the effect of something: Whoever
makes it forbidden to others makes it forbidden to him, if not
forbidden to others, not forbidden to him. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
basically has explained that in terms of being consistent in the case
where a man's wife's sister and his brother-in-law, excuse me, his wife
and his brother-in-law went to מדינת הים Medinat Hayam. *Medinat HaYam*. They
were reported dead, they turns out that they were alive. So there's
a consequence to the sister and there's a consequence, you know, potential
consequence vis-a-vis him and his wife. And reading רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi,
*Rabbi Yosei* that you have to be consistent: either they're both going
to be מותר *muttar*, they're both going to be אסור assur *assur*,
because of whether that marriage that he did to the wife's sister
is perceived of as having been binding or not, we'll have a
consistent application, we have to be consistent in terms of how we
deal with that and what the consequences of that were. So we
pick up where about six lines from the bottom. אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל Shmuel *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel*, says רב יהודה *Rav
Yehuda* in the name of שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, הלכה כרבי יוסי *halacha
k'Rabbi Yosei*, we rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi Yosei*. Now
there are different versions of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosei*, so
it's not exactly clear which one this is going like. So I
think רש"י *Rashi* says here one minute.
Yeah, if you look at רש"י *Rashi*, four lines down in the
wide lines, line starts with word יוסי *Yosei*. רש"י *Rashi* says, קסלקא
דעתך כולה מילתא דרבי יוסי קאי שמואל Shmuel *kasalka daitach kula milta
d'Rabbi Yosei qai Shmuel*. ואמר *V'amar*, so he's going on all parts
of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosei*'s statement, דהאי דמצרא אישה הנישאת
לאחר משום שמא יאמרו גירש זה ונשא זה *d'hai d'mitz'ra isha haniseis
l'acher mishum shema yomru gerash zeh v'nasas zeh*, whatever. ומחזיר גרושתו משניסת
*U'mahazir gerushaso mishenises*,
so the concern is only when people will perceive it as having
been a possible marriage. וכל היכא דמימא הך מצרא ואפילו היא אחות
ארוסתו *V'chol heicha d'mima hach mitz'ra v'afilu hi achos arusaso*. Okay, so
meaning, I probably should have read all that, that might have been
a little confusing, but anyway, what רש"י *Rashi* is saying is, is
that the question about what will be Leah's status and what will
be the implications for Rachel is a question about whether people had
perceived the marriage that Reuven did with Leah as having been binding
or not. And one of the reasons they may or may not
have was whether he had been only קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* with Rachel.
Do you remember, this was a discussion yesterday, or even נישואין *nissuin*.
If it was only קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* with Rachel, it's possible they
perceived his marriage to Leah as binding. If it had been נישואין
*nissuin* with his real wife Rachel, then people would not have perceived
it as such.
Only נישואין *nissuin* with Leah?
No, with Rachel, because then they'll realize that if that marriage was
binding, there's no way that they will have perceived the marriage with
Leah as having been binding.
If
you just make קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* with Leah, then there's no problem
at all.
Yeah, but that we're not talking about. So let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. מתקיף לה רב יוסף *Maskif lah Rav Yosef*, so רב
יוסף *Rav Yosef* asked on that: ומי אמר שמואל Shmuel הכי *umi
amar Shmuel hachi*, did שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* really say that? דשמואל לטעמיה
*D'Shmuel l'taamei*, that שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says. והא איתמר *V'ha itmar*, יבמה
yevamah *yevama*, sister-in-law. רב אמר *Rav amar*, הרי היא
כאשת איש ke'eshet ish *harei hi k'eishesh ish*, she should be treated
like a married woman. ושמואל אמר *U'shmuel amar*, אינה כאשת איש ke'eshet
ish. *einah k'eishesh ish*, she shouldn't be treated like a married woman.
Well, you know, that's very clear. I mean, what the heck are
you talking about? What's the context? Okay, so we're going to assume
that the following is the context of רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav
Huna*'s interpretation of this debate of רב *Rav* and שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*.
ואמר רב הונא Rav Huna *V'amar Rav Huna*, כגון שקידש אחיו את
האישה *k'gon shekidesh achiv es ha'isha*, so for example, a man's brother
married a
woman. So Shimon let's say married a woman. והלך לו למדינת הים
*V'halach lo limedinat hayam*, and then Shimon went to a faraway country.
ושמעה שמת אחיו *V'sham'ah shemeis achiv*, and it seems like now Shimon
is dead based on a report. ועמד ונשא אשתו *V'amad v'nasas ishto*,
and he went ahead and he did קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* to his
sister-in-law. Okay, so this is a classic case of a woman whose
husband is reported as dead, except the man who married her is
the brother-in-law thinking he is doing יבום Yibum *yibum*. Okay, now the
reason it's going to be different than a normal case is, when
it turns out the husband is alive, people in hindsight will not
have seen this thing that happened, they won't have seen it as
a קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*, because they'll say of course, well now that
the brother's alive, clearly... wasn't married to the brother, you can't be
married to your, you know, even if your husband had given you
a גט, get, you're not allowed to be married to his brother
afterwards, right? The איסור issur of marrying your husband's, your husband's brother
applies even after divorce. So now that it turned out that the
husband was alive, nobody will perceive in hindsight her marriage to ראובן
Reuven as having been binding.
Why not? Well, I thought we said it's only קידושין. kiddushin, It
was a תנאי בכתובה. tnai biktuvah.
So then there's many reasons why,
this is the case of קידושין.
kiddushin, No, no, it was קידשה. kiddsha. Oh, so now we're, oh,
so right, so the point as Michael says is correct, so the
difference possibly being, but however, since there was only a קידושין, kiddushin,
maybe we'll think that maybe people will be able to perceive it
as binding, thank you, because maybe they'll think that that fell through.
So let's take a look. Okay, והלך וקדש אחת משתי אחיות Ve-halach
ve-kadesh achat mi-shtei achayot ואמר לה ונתת אשה ve-amar lah ve-natata isha
ורב אמר הרי היא כשת איש ואסורה ליבם. ve-Rav amar harei hi
ke-eshet ish ve-asura leyabam. That once it turns out that the husband
is alive, has all the negative consequences because we are concerned that
people will perceive it as binding. Why? Because as Michael pointed out,
since the original thing was only קידושין, kiddushin it's possible even in
hindsight people will think that the original thing didn't go through and
therefore the second thing was binding. ושמואל אמר אין אשת איש שרויה
לו. ve-Shmuel amar ein eshet ish shruya lo. No, even though it's
only קידושין, kiddushin, that doesn't matter. People don't think, oh, maybe the,
maybe you know, there's a תנאי, tnai, and people in hindsight look
at the marriage to ראובן Reuven and say clearly it wasn't binding
because she had already been married to שמעון Shimon and clearly she
never could have been married to the brother. Okay, so we see
according to this read of the debate that שמואל Shmuel says that
even if you began with קידושין, kiddushin we're still afraid that people
will perceive this thing as having been a possible marriage. So you
get it? So what we had said was that if לאה's Leah's
marriage to ראובן Reuven was only קידושין, kiddushin.
people, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, אין אשת איש, ein eshet ish, thank
you. So שמואל Shmuel, says that even if it's only קידושין, kiddushin?
right? And people in hindsight will not see it as marriage, because
they'll have thought that, they won't think that the קידושין kiddushin. was
בתנאי. bitnai. So applying it here, even if ראובן's Reuven's marriage to
רחל Rachel had only been by קידושין, kiddushin in hindsight people will
not look at his marriage of לאה Leah as having been a
marriage, right? If it turns out רחל Rachel is alive, they'll say
oh he can never have been married to לאה. Leah. The same
way שמואל Shmuel, says if it turns out that the first husband
is alive, they'll say he never could have been married to the
brother. Okay, and the fact that the first marriage was קידושין kiddushin.
won't make a difference. So you see that שמואל Shmuel is willing
to be lenient even if the first marriage is קידושין. kiddushin, So
how could שמואל Shmuel say that we're strict if the first marriage
is קידושין? kiddushin, So the גמרא Gemara says, ושמואל אמר אין אשת
איש שרויה לו ve-Shmuel amar ein eshet ish shruya lo אמר ליה
אביי ממאי דכי אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי אדרבי יצחק נפחא קאמר.
amar leh Abaye memai de-chi amar Shmuel halacha ke-Rabbi Yossi
ad-Rabbi Yitzchak Napcha ka-amar. How do you know when שמואל said we
rule like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi it was the second interpretation of
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi which had the case of the stringency when
the first marriage was only a קידושין. kiddushin דילמא אדרבי אמי קאמר.
dilma ad-Rabbi Ami ka-amar.
Maybe it was the first interpretation of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi Again,
I won't try to remind you about all we discussed yesterday, but
the first interpretation didn't make this distinction between whether the marriage was
קידושין kiddushin or נשואין. nissu'in. ואי נמי אדרבי יצחק נפחא. ve-i nami
ad-Rabbi Yitzchak Napcha. And even if it's going on the second interpretation,
ממאי דאפסול. memai de-apsul.
How do you know when he says we rule like רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yossi. he's saying we rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, in
the stringent case of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi when the first marriage
was קידושין. kiddushin, ודילמא אאינו פסול. ve-dilma a-eino pasul.
Maybe he's talking about when it's not an invalidity. Again, remember what
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi said was two things. He said in this
scenario over here, okay, if the marriage to רחל Rachel was only
קידושין, kiddushin, people will perceive this as having been okay, and then
she's, therefore it's, we'll perceive this as having been a marriage, and
therefore she's אסורה לברק asura le-Barak and he's אסור לרחל. assur le-Rachel.
That's רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose. being strict, that in a case where
this was only a קידושין, Kiddushin? not only is לאה Leah אסורה
לברק, asura le-Barak, he's even אסור to go back to his wife.
That's a strict application of רבי יוסי. Consistent,
the status of לאה Leah to ברק Barak is the same as
him to רחל, Rachel, consistent, but consistent לחומרא le-chumra in a case
where this was only קידושין Kiddushin because people will have perceived this
as having been binding. In a case where this was נשואין nissu'in
and people won't have perceived this as being binding, we're going to
be lenient in both cases and we'll even let לאה Leah go
back. So we say דוקא davka שמואל says we rule like רבי
יוסי, maybe all he meant to say when we rule like רבי
יוסי is that we would be always מקיל meikel the same way
we're מקיל meikel by רחל, Rachel, okay, and that if he can
go back to רחל, Rachel, לאה Leah can go back to ברק.
Barak. But he didn't mean to say that if this was just
a קידושין Kiddushin, we're going to be strict here. No, even if
this is just a קידושין, Kiddushin? we're not going to be strict
here. In hindsight, we're going to say this obviously wasn't binding and
we're going to be lenient across the board.
And lenient by what again?
Lenient by the גמרא Gemara says that the same way he can
go back to רחל, Rachel, לאה Leah can go back to ברק.
Barak. Now, we had said that that was in a context when
this was נשואין. nissu'in. But the גמרא Gemara is saying maybe שמואל
just means to say whether this is נשואין nissu'in or קידושין, Kiddushin
you know, either way we're going to be lenient and let him
go back to רחל Rachel and לאה Leah go back to ברק.
Barak. So maybe all he meant to do when he פסקן paskan
like רבי יוסי was to say that we would be always מקיל
meikel and the same way we'd always let him go back to
רחל, Rachel, we would let לאה Leah go back to ברק. Barak.
And he meant to be always
מקיל. meikel. Not contradicting but about where you always let Leah go
back
to Baruch.
No, only because it's a case of sister, not in a normal
case of the husband being alive. Because it's a sister, so in
hindsight everybody understands that what's unique about this and also the other
case that we introduced when she married the brother and it turned
out the husband was alive, was that in those cases in a
normal case if it turns out the husband is alive, one of
the reasons of all the stringencies, like we said, is not just
to fine her, but because it looked like she had been married
to guy number two. And what we're exploring here is that there's
some cases that in hindsight it won't have looked like she was
married to guy number two. Because once they see the husband's alive,
if the normal husband is alive they could still think it was
like she was married to guy number two in hindsight, because maybe
the husband had divorced her from מדינת הים. Medinat Hayam So it's
still even in hindsight still looks like they were married. But in
a case where the wife's sister, his first wife who was the
wife's sister, the sister of the second woman, was alive, then it's
impossible he had been married to the second woman, even after divorce
he wouldn't have been able to be married to her. Or in
the case where the second husband is her first husband's brother and
it turns out that the first husband's alive, then it'll be impossible
in hindsight to think that she was married to the second guy,
because as long as the first husband's alive, even after divorce it
wouldn't have been binding. So that's the חידוש chiddush that we are
introducing here, cases where in hindsight it would've been impossible for it
to see it as she had been married to the second guy
and therefore can we be lenient? Okay, so it's worth appreciating that
that is the idea that we are introducing. In a case of
wife's sister or husband's brother and the guy turns up alive or
the woman turns up alive, that we can be lenient and let
the woman go back to her husband because nobody will ever be
able to have perceived what happened to have been an actual marriage
to the second guy or to the second woman. And the question
is can we be lenient even in a case where the first
marriage was just a קידושין? Kiddushin? So people might have thought that
maybe that didn't actually go through and maybe the second one is
good. And that what we're saying now is according to this position
of שמואל, this read of שמואל, that no, we don't have to
be worried about it even in a קידושין Kiddushin, case. Even if
it was just a קידושין, kiddushin the second one will not have
looked at as being binding and we'll let everybody go back to
their original spouses. Yes?
The prohibition against marrying someone's relatives takes place with קידושין? kiddushin, Yes.
So that is logical.
Yes. Okay, but the point the question was that maybe people will
think that the קידושין kiddushin was פגום, pagum, didn't go through and
so on and so forth. We're not concerned about that. Yes.
This case of brothers couldn't have been a יבם yavam marrying?
Not in hindsight once the first guy turns out alive.
When she was actually he
could have done יבמה yevama with
yes, but the question is when the guy was in מדינת הים
Medinas Ha-yam, and we thought he was dead, obviously people perceived the
second thing as a binding marriage. The question is is that even
when it turns out that the guy is alive and shows up
alive or the woman shows up alive, if now nobody will have
perceived it in hindsight as binding, right? Then maybe we shouldn't apply
all these stringencies. So this is very important and it again reminds
us that these stringencies are not just a fine. Part of the
reason of all these stringencies, if not the reason, is because it
results from the fact that it looked like she was married to
somebody else. But the point is it doesn't have to look like
that even in hindsight, okay? And when it can't look like that
in hindsight because it turned out the brother was alive or it
turned out the wife's sister was alive, then in hindsight it's impossible
that that would have been perceived of as a marriage in
hindsight, right? בשעת מעשה B'sha'at ma'aseh yes, but in hindsight no, then
it shouldn't have these negative consequences. And that's what שמואל means to
rule like רבי יוסי. And the only question on the table is
can we even be lenient in a case where the first marriage
was just קידושין? kiddushin And the answer is based on one read
of the debate of רב ושמואל, Rav v'Shmuel, yes, even in that
case we can be lenient.
The logic legally is that in hindsight you realize that there's no
foundation for all the stringencies.
Right. Exactly.
That's a powerful point.
Right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אוקיי, Okay, אי נמי,
Inami, or you could say ממאי דהאי סברא דאמר רב הונא, Mimmay
de-hai sevara d'amar Rav Huna, how do you know רב הונא is
the right interpretation of the debate of רב ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel which
has שמואל saying that even if the first marriage was קידושין, kiddushin
we're not we say that people will still in hindsight realize that
the second marriage was not binding. דילמא ליתא לדרב הונא, Dilma leita
l'd'Rav Huna, maybe רב הונא is not the right interpretation of רב
ושמואל Rav v'Shmuel כלל. klal. וברב המנונא קמיפלגי, U'v'Rav Hamnuna kamipalgi, when
they debate is a sister-in-law like a married woman? It's a very
cryptic debate. Maybe they're debating something else. דאמר רב המנונא, D'amar Rav
Hamnuna, שומרת יבם שזינתה, shomeret yavam she-zinta, if a woman awaiting יבום
Yibbum or חליצה Chalitzah sleeps with another man, אסורה ליבמה, asura l'yivama,
she's forbidden to her brother-in-law.
That's a very straightforward interpretation of the question. Is a יבמה yevama
like a married woman? Well, what's the question? If she sleeps with
another man, is it like adultery? Does she become forbidden to her
brother-in-law? Okay, רב אמר הרי היא כאשת איש ופסולה בזינות Rav amar
harei hi ke'eshet ish u'psula bezinus says that when she sleeps with
another man it's like adultery and she becomes forbidden to the brother-in-law.
ושמואל אמר אינה כאשת איש ולא פסולה בזינות.
u'Shmuel amar eina ke'eshet ish v'lo
psula bezinus. And Shmuel says not that way. ואי נמי בקידושין תופסין
ביבמה קמיפלגי, v'i nami bekiddushin topsin biyevama kamifligi, or let's let's remind
ourselves of another debate about the sister-in-law. Can marriage be binding if
he accepts marriage from another man before חליצה? chalitza? רב אמר הרי
היא כאשת איש Rav amar harei hi ke'eshet ish that the זיקה
zika to the brother-in-law is like is like she's married, ולא תפסי
בה קידושין v'lo tapsi ba kiddushin
and therefore if she accepts marriage from another man it won't be
binding. ושמואל אמר אינה כאשת איש ותפסי בה קידושין u'Shmuel amar eina
ke'eshet ish v'tapsi ba kiddushin no if she accepts marriage from another
man it will be binding. גמרא Gemara says האיפכא בהא זימנא ha'ifcha
beha zimna but we know they debated this issue once before? חדא
מכלל חברתה איתמר. chada miklal chaverta itmar. Fine, it was said in
one case and therefore it was inferred in the other. But maybe
that's exactly their debate. So the last two cases are nice because
they sort of go hand in hand. How much is her relationship
to the brother-in-law like she's married to him, which is a very
straight read of Rav and Shmuel. How much is it like she's
married with two implications: how much is sleeping with another man like
adultery and how much and is it possible for her to be
married to another man? Okay, but we ended that whole discussion about
the woman again, to remind ourselves, I mean we just spent a
good few minutes discussing it, but to remind ourselves the important point
about this is not just that the husband can go back to
his wife if he had married the sister. In a way that's
relatively, I think for most of us relatively obvious, right? How would
a woman become forbidden because he had married the sister? The bigger
חידוש chiddush is, I mean the גמרא Gemara explored it but that's
pretty obvious, the bigger חידוש chiddush is is that maybe even a
woman who married another man can go back to her husband in
special cases where in hindsight we will not have looked at that
as having been binding. And those special cases are where she married
the brother or the special case is where she married her sister's
husband. And those cases maybe even if it turns out the husband's
alive she can go back to her first husband. Okay, next משנה.
Mishna. Yes, טוב. Yes.
Just to figure out like how how do they envision this all
working? Because on the one hand it's clear that people had to
know somebody you married somebody, this needs the approval of a בית
דין beit din or whatever. Right. Right.
On the other
hand, they've had to establish all these rules so that you know
when they establish these rules how do they envision that working? Obviously
that's only going to work you know all these חומרות chumrot and
and things like that only going to work...
Right, if בית דין beit din is overseeing all of the marriages
and if sometimes people are going ahead and doing it on their
own. Right. Right.
Yeah, it's a good point. I mean you could sort of ask
the question about what goes on right now like in Israel. You
know, some people decide to you know to sort of do a
work around the whole רבנות rabbanut and do their private marriage ceremonies
let alone go to Cyprus and get married or whatever. You know,
but every now and then your paths cross with the whole you
know establishment,
exactly, bureaucracy and authority and they're going to say what they're going
to say about it. But but you're right. I mean it is
interesting. Sometimes people I guess doing whatever they're doing but we're going
to have our rules, what are we going to do if it
comes under our you know jurisdiction? But yeah, but yeah.
There's a question in the לשון. lashon. The חדא מכלל חברתה איתמר,
chada miklal chaverta itmar, so is it a תירוץ? teretz?
Yeah, even though Rav and Shmuel already debated this so why would
they debate it again with this language of כאשת איש if they've
already debated תפסי קידושין? tapsi kiddushin? Point is they really only debated
one case and then it was reframed and it was restated in
a different way in another situation. So they're not saying they're not
having the same debate twice. They had the debate once and we
applied it from one case to the next.
In other words, here's one case in which it kind of comes
out of the general...
No, meaning we had one one debate מחלוקת רב ושמואל machlokes Rav
v'Shmuel whether קידושין kiddushin is תופסין ביבמה. tophsin biyevama. We had another
מחלוקת רב ושמואל machlokes Rav v'Shmuel whether a יבמה yevamah is כאשת
איש. We said that it meant the same thing. If it meant
the same thing why did they debate it twice with two different
sets of terminology? And the answer is they didn't debate it twice.
They only debated it one with one set of terminology and we
inferred, we sort of restated the second one based on the first
one.
So, חדא מכלל חברתה chada miklal chaverta exactly.
Okay. משנה. Mishnah אמרו לו מתה אשתך, Amru lo mesa ishtecha,
they said to a man your wife died, ונשא אחותה מאביה, venasa
achosa me'aviha, this is going to be a fun case, it'll go
pretty quickly which is good because we're behind, and he married her
sister. Okay like we said before.
Then they said מתה, mesa, then the sister then the second wife
went on a trip and they told him she had died, ונשא
אחותה מאמה venasa achosa me'ima and then he married and then he
married his wife's sister on her mother's side. So basically, I'm just
going to tell you what the case is and then we'll read.
It's a nice diagram.
He keeps on he keeps on marrying women, they keep on going
on trips and being reported as and being reported as dead. Okay?
So the women he marries is, so first you've got you
know woman one and two that share a that share a father,
okay, that share a father but have different mothers. Okay? So they've
got different mothers, alright, but they share a father.
Then sister
three... Okay, and then sister five, right, exactly. Okay, and he's going
to marry all of these sequentially because everyone is reported dead, goes
away and is reported dead after he marries them. Okay?
Oh boy, when did this ever happen?
Right, right. So, okay, so, ונסב אחת מהנה מתה ונסב אחת מאביה
מתה, Venasav achas me-hena meisa, venasav achas me-aviha meisa, and then they
tell him she's dead, ונסב אחת מאמה, venasav achas me-ima,
he marries the next one from the mother, ונמצאו כולן קיימות, venimtzu
kulan kayamos, they're all alive, okay, and he's been marrying them sequentially.
מותר בראשונה בשלישית ובחמישית, Mutar ba-rishona ba-shlishis u-va-chamishis,
he can stay married to wife one, three, and five. Why can
he stay married to one, three, and five? This was the one
he first married. So when he married two, was it binding? No,
he was marrying his wife's sister. So this wasn't binding. Okay, when
he married three, was it binding? Yes, because three was not related
to one. Right? So when he married four, was it binding? No,
because that was wife three's sister. When he married five, was it
binding? Yes, because five is not related to three, right? Five is
only related to four, four is only related to three, right? You're
only related to the one that is proximate to you. What?
Oh, I see. Okay, fine.
Three wives. Three wives, okay. מותר בראשונה בשלישית ובחמישית ופוטר צרותיהן, Mutar
ba-rishona ba-shlishis u-va-chamishis u-poter tzaroseihen, they're all completely legitimately his wives. So
if in a case where he would die and the brother would
do יבום Yibbum or חליצה Chalitza with one of them, it would
get the other two off. ואסור בשנייה וברביעית, Va-assur ba-shniya u-va-reviis, the
wife two and four are not his wives, ואין ביאת אחת מהן
פוטרת צרתה. ve-ein bias achas me-hen poteret tzartah. And if he were
to die and a brother would do ביאה bi-ah with wife two
or four, well they wouldn't be a wife, so it wouldn't get
the other wives off the hook. ואם בא על השנייה לאחר מיתת
הראשונה, Ve-im ba al ha-shniya le-achar misas rishona, now let's say it
turns out that one had legitimately died. When they told him one
was dead, actually that was the one true report. So in that
case, his marriage to two is good, right, because one was legitimately
dead, and three would be no good. And then the marriage to
four would be good, and five would be no good. Okay, ואם
בא על השנייה לאחר מיתת הראשונה, ve-im ba al ha-shniya le-achar misas
rishona, the first one had genuinely died, מותר בשנייה וברביעית ופוטר צרותיהן,
mutar ba-shniya u-va-reviis u-poter tzaroseihen,
then two and four are his wives and if he dies then
an act of ביאה bi-ah for one would exempt the other. ואסור
בשלישית ובחמישית, Va-assur ba-shlishis u-va-chamishis, three and five are not his wives
and he's forbidden to them because now they're his wife's sisters.
Right? This doesn't mean he's just not married to them, it's also
saying that he can't sleep with them if he wanted to because
they're obviously now his wife's sister. ואין ביאת אחת מהן פוטרת צרתה,
Ve-ein bias achas me-hen poteret tzartah, and if a brother did יבום
Yibbum. or חליצה Chalitza to one, it wouldn't help the other ones
because these aren't the real wives.
Okay, so wait, the צרות tzaros here are the ones that they're
then naming, right, the שלישית? shlishis?
One, three, and five are the צרות, tzaros, right.
Why does the לשון lashon repeat itself? Like in other words, it
says צרות tzaros and then they number them, and that is to
say three and five, right?
No, because it just switched to a case of יבום. Yibbum In
a case of יבום Yibbum where you did יבום Yibbum with one
wife, would it get the other, if you did יבום Yibbum, with
woman number one, would it get three and five off the hook
or not? So in the case of יבום, Yibbum. we're using the
term of צרות. tzaros. Alright, now, now that was a very easy
case, but okay, it was fun. Now, בן תשע שנים ויום אחד.
Ben tesha shanim ve-yom echad. Now, let's say we're going to go
back, all the way jump back to יבום. Yibbum We have somehow
bizarrely been on this big discussion of a husband going to מדינת
הים, which had really very little to do with הלכות יבום, Hilchos
Yibbum, I mean here and there it touched on something, but now
we're getting back to a straight הלכות יבום. Hilchos Yibbum. בן תשע
שנים ויום אחד. Ben tesha shanim ve-yom echad. You have a brother
that is nine years old and a day. Nine years old and
a day, an act of sex is considered an act of sex.
But presumably he cannot do, even though he does an act of
sex, it does not create a legitimate יבום Yibbum? because he's not
an adult. So what would be the consequence of him having sex
with his sister-in-law awaiting יבום? Yibbum
Okay, you got it, basically one of the surviving brothers is nine
years old and a day. So, בן תשע שנים ויום אחד הוא
פוסל על ידי אחים. Ben tesha shanim ve-yom echad hu posel al
yedei achim. He invalidates the, you know, the brothers' like, you know,
opportunities, which means if he goes ahead and does יבום Yibbum with
the sister-in-law, with the widow, then none of the brothers can do
יבום Yibbum. anymore. Even though his act was not fully binding, it
was meaningful enough, as the גמרא's Gemara going to say, like מאמר.
maamar. We already know there are all these quasi-acts which are enough
to disqualify everybody else from doing it. So if he does ביאה
bi-ah with her, it disqualifies the brothers. ואחים פוסלים על ידו. Ve-achim
poslim al yado. And if the brothers would do an act with
the widow, whether that would be ביאה bi-ah or חליצה, Chalitza, which
would be obvious, or even מאמר maamar or גט, get remember those
Rabbinic middle acts, that would, that would get him out of the
picture.
So what's the חידוש? chiddush? His ביאה bi-ah is ביאה, bi-ah, so
what's the חידוש? chiddush?
Because even though his ביאה bi-ah is ביאה, bi-ah, it doesn't, since
he's not yet an adult, it's not yet an act of יבום.
yibum. It's still a minor. אלא הוא פוסל תחילה ואחים פוסלים תחילה
וסוף. Ella hu posel techilla ve-achim poslim techilla ve-sof. What he does
only, only kicks them out of the picture if he's the first
one to do it, whereas what they do will, will kick, kick
him out of out of the picture even if they come second.
What does that mean? כיצד. Keitzad. בן תשע שנים ויום אחד שבא
על יבמתו. Ben tesha shanim veyom echad sheba al yevamto. Basically, brother
died, and then this nine year old and one day had sex
with the widow. That's פסלה לכולהו. paslah l'kulehu. That kicks that disqualifies
now the brothers from being able to do יבום. yibum באו עליה
אחים ועשו בה מאמר נתנו גט או חלצו. Ba'u aleha achim ve'asu
bah ma'amar natnu get o chaltzu. Now let's say after he went
ahead and did this and kicked them out of the picture, they
still went ahead and did an act. Whether the act was יבום
yibum. or the act was חליצה, chalitzah, or it was one of
the rabbinic acts of גט get or מאמר. ma'amar. That act that
they did, even though they came second, is meaningful enough to now
kick him out of the picture, and now he can't go ahead,
even when he becomes an adult, and complete and do a real
יבום. yibum. You understand? So he got in there, he disqualified them.
If they were to do nothing when he became an adult, he
would then have sex with her again and it would be a
legitimate יבום. yibum But because they did something now, even though they
came second, that kicks him out of the picture.
After his ביאה? biyah?
But if he came after them, they went ahead, one of the
brothers, adult brothers, did מאמר, ma'amar, and then he came and he
did מאמר ma'amar or גט get, or חליצה, chalitzah, or maybe even
an act of sex. Presumably what the משנה Mishnah is saying is
that would not be meaningful. Since the adult brothers did something first,
what he would do after would have no meaning. That's at least
what the משנה Mishnah sounds like. We'll see what the גמרא Gemara
says.
Yes, but doesn't she have to wait for him? Say nothing happens
other than the sexual act.
The first act. Yes, then she would have to wait for him.
Yeah, because now he has kicked the other brothers out of the
equation and now this can't get fully consummated till he's an adult.
Yes.
I've heard of rare instances where a woman died where a husband
died and the only brother is
a minor.
Is a minor, yeah.
So that would be the case, you'd have to wait. Okay, so
first the גמרא Gemara just says on the fun little first case
about wives one, three and five, and then it says if the
first one had died. So it says אטו כולהו לאו לאחר מיתת
ראשונה נינהו? Atu kulehu lav le'achar mitat rishona ninhu? I don't get
it. You know, all the first scenario was also that they did
it after the report of the first one's death. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, no, לאחר מיתת ראשונה
ודאי. le'achar mitat rishona vaday. The second case in the משנה Mishnah
is the first one had really died, not just reported dead, right?
When it said if the first one had died, then he's married
to two and four and not three and five. So it says
all of them is after he died? No, no, the second case
is she's really dead. You know, that she stays dead, as somebody
said, right? Not that she's just reported as dead. Okay, fine. Okay.
Maybe they come back to life.
Right. You know, this is obviously somewhere along just somebody's going to
have to say the Mark Twain line, right? Which is reports of
my death have been greatly exaggerated.
So alright, so anyway. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara now continues. Alright,
she's still dead.
I'm sorry, I read the wrong line. Oh, go back.
Alright, she's still dead. Alright, בן תשע שנים ויום אחד. Ben tesha
shanim veyom echad. Alright, you'll have to remember that one. Alright, shhh.
Okay. בן תשע שנים ויום אחד. Ben tesha shanim veyom echad. תחילה
פוסל. Techila posel. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, תחילה פוסל
ובסוף לא פוסל. techila posel uvesof lo posel. So the משנה Mishnah.
seems to be saying clearly, any act he does after the brothers
have done an act is not meaningful, doesn't do anything, doesn't disqualify
the other brothers. Is that true? והתניא דבי רבי אושעיא, Vehatanya d'vei
Rabbi Oshaya, Rabbi Oshaya taught in a the son of Rabbi Oshaya
taught a ברייתא, braita, העושה מאמר ביבמתו ואחר כך בא אחיו שהוא
בן תשע שנים ויום אחד עליה, Ha'oseh ma'amar biyvamto ve'achar kach ba
achiv shehu ben tesha shanim veyom echad aleha, that an adult brother
did מאמר ma'amar and then came this minor brother, nine years and
a day, and had sex with her, so he's coming second, okay?
Nevertheless, פסלה! paslah! He invalidates her to the first brother, even though
the first brother was
planning on doing יבום yibum. because he started by doing a מאמר.
ma'amar. So you see this is against the משנה. Mishnah This says
that the act of of the nine year old here is invalidates
even coming second. So the גמרא Gemara. says אמרי, Amri, so we're
going to actually now do a serious re-read of our משנה Mishnah
in order to keep it within the context of this ברייתא. braita.
So you can say, ביאה פסלה אפילו בסוף. Biyah paslah afilu besof.
You know what? You're right. If this nine year old in a
day, this young guy here, does ביאה, biyah, then a real act
of sex, then that will create problems even if he comes after
the brothers. So what does the משנה Mishnah mean when it says
the young guy, the the minor does not create problems when he
comes second? So it says מאמר תחילה פוסל בסוף לא פוסל. Ma'amar
techila posel besof lo posel. It means when he does anything other
than sex. When he does, let's say, a מאמר ma'amar or a
גט, get you know, or something like that, we're saying a מאמר.
ma'amar. So if he does an actual act of sex, that's going
to create a problem even coming second, but if he does some
of these other things, then it'll only be if he comes first.
So the גמרא says וביאה אפילו בסוף פסלה? u'viyah afilu besof paslah?
Are you telling me that an act of sex from this minor
will be a problem if it comes even if it comes second?
והקתני? Vehatani? But the משנה Mishnah doesn't sound that way. The משנה
mishna, says, אלא הוא פוסל תחילה והן תחילה וסוף, ela hu posel
techila vehan techila vesof, he invalidates only at the beginning, they do
it at the beginning and at the end. כיצד? Keitzad? And then
when it gives an example, it says בן תשע שנים ויום אחד
שבא על יבמתו, ben tesha shanim veyom echad sheba al yevamto, if
he had sex with his sister-in-law. It gives the example that he
came in first, that he did it first, right? And that sounds
like that we're talking about sex and we're saying that even
when
he... בן
תשע שנים ויום אחד הוא פוסל תחילה ואין פוסל תחילה וסוף. ben
tesha shanim veyom echad hu posel techila ve'ein posel techila vesof. A
minor creates a problem only at the beginning, but they create a
problem beginning and the end. במה דברים אמורים? Bameh devarim amurim? When
is it true that he only creates a problem at the beginning?
במאמר, bemamar, if all he's doing is מאמר, mamar, which is קידושין,
right? But קידושין that's only Rabbinic because it's a case of יבום.
yibum, אבל ביאה, Aval bia, but if it's a real act of
sex, פוסל אותה אפילו בסוף, posel ota afilu besof, that'll create a
problem even at the end. כיצד בן תשע שנים ויום אחד הבא
על יבמתו, Keytzad ben tesha shanim veyom echad haba al yevamto, פסל
על ידי אחים. pasal al yedei achim. How would it be if
he basically had sex? And now the Gemara's reading the case in
the Mishnah, a very strange read of the case of the Mishnah,
if he had sex with his sister-in-law after they had already done
something like מאמר, mamar, that would still create a problem. So it's
a very difficult read
of the Mishnah, right, seals the deal.
Right, it's a very difficult read of the Mishnah, but in order
to make it consistent with the Baraita, we are now saying that
when this minor does an act of sex, it is worse than,
not worse, but it is it is more
powerful
and therefore effective even when it comes later. Okay, so let's get
a little bit further, okay? Because we're about. Okay. Oh, now the
Gemara says like this: ומי אית ליה מאמר כלל? Umi it lei
mamar klal? So now you're saying fine, so sex is powerful for
a minor and therefore even when it comes second, it's going to
have an impact. But מאמר mamar will be weaker and that'll have
an impact only at the beginning. But is that really true? That
מאמר mamar is meaningful at all for a minor? Okay. ומי אית
ליה מאמר כלל? Umi it lei mamar klal? Maybe, you know, according
to the Mishnah, the Mishnah says if all he has is sex,
that's the only thing that's meaningful and that only at the beginning.
And maybe according to the Mishnah, מאמר mamar would be nothing. You've
upped the ante. You've said that sex is powerful for a minor
and even at the end, and that מאמר mamar is meaningful at
the beginning. So is that really true? Is מאמר mamar meaningful at
all for this for this minor? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught in a
Baraita, בן תשע שנים ויום אחד, ben tesha shanim veyom echad, this
minor, הוא פוסל בדבר אחד, hu posel bedavar echad, he can invalidate,
you know, could disqualify the brothers with one act, ואחים פוסלין על
ידו בארבעה דברים, veachim poslin al yado bearba'ah devarim, and they can
invalidate him with four acts. הוא פוסל על ידי אחים בביאה, Hu
posel al yedei achim bevia, his act of sex disqualifies the brothers.
Sounds like it, pretty clear. ואחים פוסלין על ידו בביאה במאמר בגט
ובחליצה, Veachim poslin al yado bevia bemamar beget uvechalitza, and for them
any of the acts disqualifies him. So again
it makes it pretty clear that for him the only meaningful act
is sex. So the Gemara says, again, tries to get out of
it, no, ביאה דפסלה בין בתחילה בין בסוף פסיקא ליה. bia dapasla
bein betechila bein besof pesika lei. Since sex for him has a
power whether at the beginning or at the end, that's something that
sort of is the one act that's always meaningful for the minor
and that's the one we're talking about. Okay. מאמר דבתחילה פסל ובסוף
לא פסל לא פסיקא ליה. Mamar debetechila pasal ubesof lo pasal lo
pesika lei.
But מאמר, mamar, which is only meaningful at the beginning, we're not
talking about it. So although
this Baraita sounds, it makes the list. Although this Baraita sounds like
he only has one thing, no, we're only listing in this list
the things that are always going to be, you know, effective acts,
meaningful acts. So therefore ביאה bia is always meaningful. The others are
not always meaningful. But what we have done is we have now
upped the ante, you know, from the Mishnah. The Mishnah sounds very
clearly and this Baraita that the only thing that's meaningful is ביאה
bia and that even that only at the beginning. And we've said
no, ביאה's bia meaningful even at the end, and the other acts
are going to also be meaningful if they come at the beginning.
Okay. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught. I'm sorry.
No, he can't do a גט get, though, right?
Yes, presumably he can. Well, we've only said מאמר. mamar. We'll worry
about the other ones later. איתמר נמי אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
יש לו גט. Itmar nami amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel yesh lo
get. There it answers your case, Michael. So once we're saying that
an act of מאמר mamar is meaningful if it comes at the
beginning, also an act of גט, get meaningful enough to disqualify the
brothers. וכן אמר רב תחליפא בר אבימי יש לו מאמר. Vechein amar
Rav Tachlifa bar Avimi yesh lo mamar. Test... the only thing we
haven't mentioned is חליצה, chalitza, presumably that would also be true. תניא
נמי הכי יש לו גט יש לו מאמר דברי רבי מאיר. Tanya
nami hachi yesh lo get yesh lo mamar divrei Rabbi Meir. Okay,
at least if it comes in the beginning it is meaningful and
we're now trying to say Rabbi Meir is also we're trying to
read him into our Mishnah as well. וסבר רבי מאיר יש לו
גט? Vesavar Rabbi Meir yesh lo get? Does Rabbi Meir really say
that if he gives a גט get. even at the beginning it'll
be meaningful? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught in a Baraita, עשו ביאת בן
תשע כמאמר בגדול, asu biat ben tesha kemamar begadol, that they made
the act of sex by this nine-year-old, by this minor, like an
act of מאמר, mamar, right? Now, now you understand the point of
that comparison. What does the act of מאמר mamar of an adult
do? It doesn't seal the deal, but it disqualifies the other brothers.
And that's exactly what this ביאה bia does. It doesn't seal the
deal, but it disqualifies the other brothers. So they gave it the
power of מאמר mamar of an adult. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir
omer,
but מאמר mamar of a kid should be like nothing though.
What, so wait a minute. Okay, but we haven't discussed that. But
maybe it's, maybe it's enough at the beginning. This is going to
be good even at the end.
רבי מאיר אומר עשו חליצת בן תשע כגט בגדול. Rabbi Meir omer
asu chalitzat ben tesha keget begadol. They made the חליצה chalitza of
a minor like a גט. get Okay now ואי איתא, ve'i ita,
if it's true that Rabbi Meir holds that a גט get, is
meaningful by a minor,
לתני כגיטו. litni kegito. Why did they have to say they made
his חליצה chalitza like an adult. Say they made his חליצה Chalitza
like his גט, get if we are assuming that his גט get
also was powerful. And they really are and here they would be
the same, because his גט get? would only be meaningful at the
beginning, and his חליצה Chalitza would only be meaningful at the beginning.
Right? So why didn't it say his חליצה Chalitza is like his
גט? get We understand why they want to say his ביאה bi'ah
is like an adult's מאמר ma'amar to say it's powerful even at
the end. But here his חליצה Chalitza and his גט get? are
both effective only at the beginning, why did we compare it to
an adult's גט? get. That would indicate that maybe he doesn't have
a גט. get, So the גמרא says אמר רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע: Amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua: No, אית ליה וזוטר. is
lei vezutar.
He does have a גט, get. but it is not as powerful
as an adult's גט. get. And therefore when we wanted to talk
about his חליצה, Chalitza, we wanted to compare it to an adult's
גט. get, In what way is it not as powerful? לרבן גמליאל
דאמר אין גט אחר גט, L'Rabban Gamliel d'amar ein get achar get,
we remember a whole debate if one brother gives a גט, get
will another brother's גט get be, you know, effective vis-a-vis him and
other things and all these, I'm not going to deal with all
the consequences. But according to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that says a
second brother's גט get after the first is not meaningful, הני מילי
בגדול אחר גדול ובקטן אחר קטן, hani mili begadol achar gadol uvekatan
achar katan, that's when they're all the same level. אבל בגדול אחר
קטן, Avel begadol achar katan, if an adult gives a גט get,
after a minor, מהני, mahani, then it would be effective for whatever
the consequences are. So therefore we couldn't say a minor's חליצה Chalitza
is like his גט, get, because his גט, get, right, would be
weaker than an adult's גט, get. and we want to say that
his חליצה Chalitza is equal to an adult's גט. get. And there's
a logic, right, because if you think about it, ביאה bi'ah and
חליצה Chalitza are the biblical acts, right? They're parallels, the weaker rabbinic
parallels are מאמר ma'amar and גט. get. So we're saying his ביאה
bi'ah is like an adult's מאמר, ma'amar, his חליצה Chalitza is like
an adult's גט. get Okay, so we want to compare it to
the, right, you know, it means that it has the weakness of
the קטן, katan, but when the קטן katan does the biblical act,
it's equivalent to a גדול gadol doing the rabbinic act, okay? So
the reason now what does it mean to compare it that way?
Well, to compare it to the מאמר ma'amar of an adult is
to say that it'll be effective even at the end. What does
it mean to compare the חליצה Chalitza of a קטן katan to
the גט get. of an adult? Not that it's effective at the
end, because that isn't true, only a ביאה bi'ah is effective at
the end. What it does is it says that it will now
play on the same playing field, if he does a חליצה, Chalitza,
it'll play on the same playing field as an adult's גט. get,
If it was a minor's גט, get it would always be, it
would be weaker, now it's going to be equivalent. And let's just
do the other case where it
matters, לרבנן דאמרי יש גט אחר גט, l'rabbanan d'amri yesh get achar
get, and according to the Rabbis that say that normally a גט
get, is effective after a גט, get הני מילי בגדול אחר גדול
ובקטן אחר קטן, hani mili begadol achar gadol uvekatan achar katan, that's
when they're equivalent. אבל קטן אחר גדול, Avel katan achar gadol, a
minor's גט get, after an adult, לא מהני lo mahani would not
be meaningful. But now that we're saying that a minor's חליצה Chalitza
equals an adult's גט, get, it will be meaningful coming after an
adult's גט, get, okay? So does a minor have חליצה, Chalitza, גט,
get, מאמר? ma'amar? Yes, okay, but they, number one, those
that are not ביאה bi'ah work only at the beginning, not at
the end. And number two is that at some level some of
those, like the גט, get. will be weaker than an adult's גט.
get, So a minor's חליצה Chalitza will be equivalent to an adult's
גט, get but a minor's גט get. will be weaker than an
adult's גט. get Yes, there was a question? You're going to be
quizzed on all of this tomorrow, yes, דוב. Dov. Let me just
erase the board.
Why do you say,
I understand how you lined them up, but why do you say
that the גט get is not the biblical act? גט get, is
a biblical act.
Not for a יבמה yevamah before, before יבום, yibum, right? For the
woman awaiting
יבום, yibum. the irony is that the things that are the biblical
acts for a normal woman, קידושין and גט, get are rabbinic acts
for this woman awaiting יבום. yibum The קידושין is מאמר ma'amar and
the גט get, is a גט, get, right? So yeah.
Yeah, and the second question is if a גדול gadol did מאמר
ma'amar and then the קטן katan came and ביאה, bi'ah, from a
דאורייתא d'oraisa perspective, is that adulterous?
So we're going to get a little bit into that coming up,
but not דאורייתא, d'oraisa, right? Because דאורייתא d'oraisa the מאמר ma'amar means
nothing.
So דרבנן d'rabbanan
if it's, right, but not דאורייתא, d'oraisa, yeah.
What if the minor has a child?
What if,
yeah, what's the question?
Then the יבמה has a child.
But not by
the first husband,
only by the second,
does it affect anything?
No, no. The question of, she could have had children from a
prior marriage, right, and the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum still applies,
right? The מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum, only is based on whether
the husband had, you know, whether the dead husband had kids, not
whether she's had kids.
But if there was a child from the minor, does that prevent
the other brothers from doing anything?
Well, the sex would have prevented the other brothers even before you
got to the child.
I'm just setting a case where the brothers might do something after
though.
Oh, no, you mean if they not only had sex, but have
had a kid, and then the brothers did גט, would that kick
him out of...? Presumably not. Yeah, presumably the child would not make
that, would not keep the brothers out, you know, more than the
sex did. Okay. Let's get onto the next משנה, mishna turn the
page at least. בן תשע שנים ויום אחד שבא על
יבמתו—same Ben tesha shanim ve'yom echad sheba al yevamto case, this minor
has had sex with his sister-in-law, ואחר כך בא עליה אחיו שהוא
בן תשע שנים ויום אחד, ve'achar kach ba aleha achiv she'hu ben
tesha shanim ve'yom echad, and then his brother, who is also a
minor, has sex with her—his twin, well okay, if they're exactly nine
years and a day, not minimum. Okay, פוסל על ידו, posel al
yado,
so the same way, right, an adult brother's act disqualifies him, another
minor's act, at least if it's an act of sex, right, can
also disqualify him. Okay again, if it's an act of מאמר ma'amar
from the minor, presumably not, but that only when that comes in
first, but here it's an act of sex, so that can also
פוסל posel and get him out of it. Yes, רבי שמעון אומר
לא פוסל, Rabbi Shimon omer lo posel, no,
this second act does not invalidate, this act of sex of the
minor does not invalidate the other, the first minor's act of sex.
Okay, why not, especially if we said before that it would invalidate
a brother's act, why, you know, an adult brother's act? בן תשע
שנים ויום אחד שבא על יבמתו ואחר כך בא על צרתה. Ben
tesha shanim ve'yom echad sheba al yevamto ve'achar kach ba al tzarata.
Now
this minor first went ahead and had sex with his—you know, his
brother was married to two wives—so first had sex with wife number
one, and then had sex with wife number two. So again, if
it had, the first thing had really worked, then wife number two
would have been out of the picture, she would have been, you
know, exempt. But now there's both awaiting ייבום, yibbum, so פוסל על
ידי עצמו. posel al yedei atzmo. So the same way he has
disqualified the brothers, he's now disqualified himself. פוסל על ידי posel al
yedei is a funny phrase, but
it's really effectively translated with the English word disqualifies, right? It's how
your act disqualifies somebody
else. Okay, so anyway, so he has now disqualified himself because the
act was meaningful enough with the co-wife that now he can't do
ייבום yibbum because, you know, a real act of ייבום yibbum can
only be with one of the wives, not both. בית אחד הוא
בונה ואינו בונה שני
בתים.
Bayit echad hu boneh ve'eino
boneh
shenei batim.
What, he can't be with any of them? No, once he becomes
an adult he can't consummate with either of them. Okay, רבי שמעון
אומר לא פוסל, Rabbi Shimon omer lo posel, it does not. So
Rabbi Shimon says that a minor's act coming does not invalidate—not clear
what it would do to adults—but it certainly doesn't invalidate the act
of another minor, whether it's himself or whether it's his brothers who
are minors. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. תני ותני
ברייתא, Tanei ve'tanei baraita, אמר להם רבי שמעון לחכמים, Amar lahem Rabbi
Shimon lachachamim, Rabbi Shimon said to the חכמים, Chachamim, אם ביאה ראשונה
ביאה, ביאה שנייה אינה ביאה. im biah rishonah biah, biah sheniyah einah
biah.
So rather than saying, like we've been talking about, that the sex
of the minor is like a מאמר, ma'amar, is, has like a
middle, you know, is not fully effective but quasi-effective. If it's quasi-effective,
then you can understand, right, one minor does one thing and the
other minor does another thing which is also quasi-effective and then it
gets in the way, right, or he does it with one wife
and then with the other wife. So you have two quasi-effective things
there and that creates problems. But Rabbi Shimon says it's not quasi-effective,
it's either a hundred percent or zero, it's not fifty percent. Okay,
so right, that's the question whether people are like black and white
or are they gray. So Rabbi Shimon is a black and white
guy. So he says, look, you know, make up your mind, it
either totally counts as an act of ביאה biah or counts as
zero. אם ביאה ראשונה ביאה, im biah rishonah biah, if the first
one was binding, fine, then ייבום yibbum has been done, and the
second, you know, one who comes along and does ביאה, biah, minor
who comes along and does ביאה, biah, won't have any effect. Then
ביאה שנייה אינה ביאה. biah sheniyah einah biah. ואם ביאה ראשונה אינה
ביאה, ve'im biah rishonah einah biah, and if the first one was
not binding, then ביאה שנייה נמי אינה ביאה, biah sheniyah nami einah
biah, then the second one also didn't do anything to her. So
he's saying I don't know whether it's effective or not, but I'm
not going to say it's fifty percent, it's either a hundred or
zero. So if all you've got is the first one, it doesn't
disqualify the brothers, no other brother can step in because the first
one might have been binding. But if you've got two of them
operating on the same plane, you've got two acts of sex from
minors, so clearly the second one is meaningless because either they're both
meaningless or the first one is meaningful and the second one is
meaningless. Okay, so therefore in the case of a second act of
sex from a second minor or the same minor with a different
woman, that to me is not going to do anything because it's
either a hundred percent or zero, so when it's two of the
same, the second one is going to be nothing.
What? No. So מתניתין דלא כבן עזאי, matnitin de'lo ke'Ben Azzai, our
משנה is not like Ben Azzai, דתניא, detanya, בן עזאי אומר, Ben
Azzai omer, יש מאמר אחר מאמר בשני יבמים ויבמה אחת, yesh ma'amar
achar ma'amar bishnei yevamim ve'yevamah achat, that if one brother did מאמר
ma'amar to the woman and then another brother, then the act of
the second brother, right, invalidates even on the first one, right, that's
what we've been dealing with, that a later act can invalidate even
the one who got there first. But ואין מאמר אחר מאמר בשתי
יבמות ויבם אחד. ve'ein ma'amar achar ma'amar bishtei yevamot ve'yavam echad. But
if it is two of the wives and the brother-in-law first did
מאמר ma'amar with wife one and then מאמר ma'amar with wife two.
wife two, his מאמר ma'amar with wife two would not disqualify him
from going back to wife one. And the case here of the
sex with the minor is, right, that case, it's equivalent to מאמר.
ma'amar. People here with me, right? The minor had sex with wife
one and then wife two, it says he can't go back to
wife one. That's not Ben Azai. Ben Azai said that if you
went ahead and did anything short of ייבום yibum with wife two,
you can still go back to wife number one. Okay, moving right
along. בן תשע שנים ויום אחד שבא על יבימתו ומת. ben tesha
shanim v'yom echad sheba al yevimto u'met. So he did this sex
with her, again not full ייבום, yibum, it's some type of rabbinic
מאמר ma'amar and then he died. Okay, and now this woman now,
you know, has to deal with the remaining brothers. Okay, so what's
her status vis-a-vis the remaining brothers? Biblically speaking, she still has to
have ייבום yibum or חליצה chalitza from her first husband. But rabbinically
she also needs ייבום yibum and חליצה chalitza from her second husband,
right, the act with the minor was at least rabbinically meaningful, right?
Everybody with me here? Yes? So now for the brothers, this is
a woman that has what if you might remember this case in
the Gemara זיקת שני יבמים עליה, zikas shnei yevamim aleha, right, so
that the brothers are connected to her two ways. Right?
You have, actually we could do,
we
could do Yehuda's sons if you want. Er, Onan and Shelah, okay.
So,
so there you have Tamar. Okay, so Er marries Tamar and then
Er dies. Okay, Onan while he was a minor, okay, went ahead
and has ביאה bi'ah with Tamar as a minor, so it's ביאת
קטן bi'as katan which equals מאמר, ma'amar, so it's only rabbinically binding.
And now he dies. Okay? So now Shelah, he has a זיקה
zika to Tamar from Er, that's a biblical זיקה, zika, right, because
this really halachically had no meaning, it was the ביאה bi'ah with
the minor that really halachically was nothing. So he has a זיקה
zika from Tamar, he's got to do ביאה bi'ah because it was
Er's wife, or חליצה, chalitza, and he's got a rabbinic זיקה,
zika, right, you know to Tamar from Onan. Okay, right? That's זיקת
אונן zikas onan because that was rabbinic, yes? So now Tamar to
him has זיקת שני יבמים עליה, zikas shnei yevamim aleha, the זיקה
zika of two brother-in-laws. That will never otherwise happen because if the
second one did a real ייבום דאורייתא, yibum d'oraisa, then that completely
removed Er from the picture. But in this case, right, it's got
actually both of them because one is דאורייתא d'oraisa and the second
one is דרבנן.
d'rabanan. You're saying that if Shelah does not want to marry Tamar,
he's got to perform two acts of חליצה? chalitza?
No, presumably he could do one. Right, yeah, but what we're going
to say is rabbinically, this is all rabbinic because this whole thing
here is rabbinic, but rabbinically the same way we say for example
you can't do ייבום yibum with both wives, right, we're going to
also say that you can't do ייבום yibum with two זיקות. zikos.
So he's going to have to do חליצה, chalitza, but only one
חליצה, chalitza, not two חליצות. chalitzos. Right, yeah, not two. Right. What?
And now the other. Right.
Okay, so let's take a look. In this case, מת חולצת ולא
מתייבמת, mes choletzet v'lo mityabemet, she has to do חליצה chalitza with
Shelah, not ייבום. yibum. That's
why Yehuda was pushing her off because Yehuda realized she wanted ייבום
yibum and Yehuda realized he could only do חליצה. chalitza. Okay, so
anyway, alright, that's my idea of rabbinic humor. Anyway, חולצת ולא מתייבמת.
choletzet v'lo mityabemet. נשא אשה ומת. nasa isha u'met. Now,
let's say this nine-year-old, forget ייבום, yibum, just סתם stam married a
woman. Okay, there's no קידושין with a nine-year-old.
Okay, but again, maybe it
has some type
of
rabbinic status. Let's take a look.
נשא
אשה אחרת ומת אם לא ידע את הראשונה,
nasa isha
acheres u'met im lo yada es harishona, mean, did I skip a
line? נשא אשה ומת הרי זו פטורה. nasa isha u'met harei zu
ptura. So a marriage, a ייבום yibum of a nine-year-old is like
a מאמר, ma'amar, it's a quasi-marriage and then you have to at
least do חליצה. chalitza. Okay, but a marriage of a nine-year-old to
a סתם stam woman is meaningless and if he dies you don't
even have to do חליצה. chalitza. Is that clear? Right, it's only
because it's an act of sex and ייבום yibum is about being
an act of sex that therefore it's some quasi-effective.
But if it was סתם stam a marriage to a סתם stam
woman then it would not be meaningful at all. בן תשע שנים
ויום אחד שבא על יבימתו. ben tesha shanim v'yom echad sheba al
yevimto. Now, this nine-year-old, this minor had sex with his sister-in-law. שבא
על יבימתו ומשהגדיל נשא אשה אחרת. sheba al yevimto u'mishehigdil nasa isha
acheres.
And then he's now an adult and he married wife number two.
ומת. u'met. And now he died. So you would say, okay, he's
married to both women. But only if he consummated the marriage with
the sister-in-law now that he's an adult. Is everybody clear on the
case? Yes. אם לא ידע את הראשונה. im lo yada es harishona.
Again, interesting ידע, yada, right, have sex with. If he did not
have sex with the first one משהגדיל mishehigdil from the time he
became adult then the first one is not... technically his wife. So
he's dead, he's got two wives, brothers have to do יבום, yibum
but the first one is not technically his wife. The first one
really is, the first wife is this case, right? The first
case now he's died, he's got another wife. So for the brothers,
right, they've basically have,
I'm sorry, so for Shelah, he's got now to deal with Tamar,
who's this זיקת שני יבמים, zikas shnei yevamim, right? This woman who
he can't do יבום yibum with, and wife number two, who he
actually can do יבום yibum. with if he wants. Right, is that
clear? Wife number one came through Er, but it never got fully
consummated, so she's in this weird זיקת שני יבמים zikas shnei yevamim
state, and he's got full wife number two. So in this case,
הראשונה חולצת ולא מתיבמת, harishona choletzet velo mityabemet, with Tamar he has
to do חליצה chalitza not יבום. yibum Is that rabbinic? No,
it's biblical because of Er's relationship. It's rabbinic because of his, but
it's biblical because of Er's, right? The brother is still, the brother
Shelah, right, is still, you know, is still dealing with Er's original
relationship with her. Yes, is that clear? No, you lost it?
After Onan became an adult, he went ahead and he married Devorah.
Okay, and then he dies. So Devorah is a real marriage and
Shelah has a דאורייתא de'oraisa יבום yibum obligation to Devorah.
Tamar is not a real marriage and his obligation to Tamar is
not דאורייתא, de'oraisa, but it is via through Er, it's just not
through Onan. So he cannot satisfy his obligation to Tamar by יבום
yibum because of this complicated case of זיקת שני יבמים, zikas shnei
yevamim, but he could do it with Devorah. Okay, so הראשונה חולצת
ולא מתיבמת, harishona choletzet velo mityabemet,
as far as Tamar is concerned you can only do חליצה chalitza
like we've already said, והשניה או חולצת או מתיבמת, veshniya o choletzet
o mityabemet,
and the second one he could choose, he could do יבום yibum
with the second woman if he wants. רבי שמעון אומר מיבם איזו
שירצה וחולץ לשניה. Rabbi Shimon omer miyabem eizo sheyirtze vecholetz lashniya. No,
he could do יבום yibum with either wife if he want and
חליצה chalitza with the other, which basically is a way of saying
if he wants to do יבום yibum with Tamar, he's welcome to
do יבום yibum with Tamar, but why can he do, why would
he still have to do חליצה chalitza with Devorah?
Because the
יבום yibum with Tamar might be about the Er relationship, right?
And that would not, right,
Tamar isn't really Onan's wife, so doing יבום yibum with Tamar doesn't
get Devorah off, and doing יבום yibum with Devorah doesn't get Tamar
off because Tamar's really part of the Er relationship. So remember Rabbi
Shimon says the קטן katan is not 50 percent, it's 0 or
100 percent, right? So if it is 0, then Tamar goes back
to the Er relationship and he could go ahead and do, you
know, יבום yibum with one and חליצה chalitza with the other, but
what he does with one doesn't affect the other. The only thing
he can't do is יבום yibum with both. Why? Why can't he
do יבום yibum with both? Because it could be the act of
a קטן katan is, does work and then Tamar is fully, it
could be 100 percent, not 0. If it's 0, then he's got,
he could do one with one and one with the other, and
in theory if it were 0 he could do יבום yibum with
both. Marry both. Exactly. Except if the act of Onan was 100
percent, then Onan has two full wives and you can only do
יבום yibum with one of them.
And the other one would get off the hook. So you don't
know, you have to do יבום yibum with one, you have to
do חליצה chalitza with one, and with the other you could do
יבום or חליצה chalitza because of the ספק. safek. Right. מיבם איזו
שירצה וחולץ לשניה.
Miyabem
eizo sheyirtze vecholetz lashniya.
Last line. אחד שהוא בן תשע שנים ויום אחד ואחד שהוא בן
עשרים שלא הביא שתי שערות, Echad shehu ben tesha shanim veyom echad
ve'echad shehu ben esrim shelo hevi shtei sa'arot, the same would be
true not only of a minor, but even of somebody who was
by years an adult but did not have pubic hairs would have
the same halachic status as a minor. Alright. That was fun.
And we are still behind, but
yeah.